The most beautiful love story ever told.
Beauty and the Beast is a romance, family,
animation film directed by Gary Trousdale.
Follow the adventures of Belle, a bright young woman who finds herself in the
castle of a prince who's been turned into a mysterious beast.
With the help of the castle's enchanted staff, Belle soon learns the most
important lesson of all -- that true beauty comes from within.
Belle (voice), played by Paige O'Hara.
Beast (voice), played by Robby Benson.
Gaston (voice), played by Richard White.
Lumiere (voice), played by Jerry Orbach.
Cogsworth (voice), played by David Ogden Stiers.
Mrs. Potts (voice), played by Angela Lansbury.
Beauty and the Beast is a 1991 American animated musical romantic fantasy film produced by Walt Disney
Feature Animation, directed by Gary Trousdale and Kirk Wise, and written by Linda Woolverton.
Based on the French fairy tale, the film stars Paige O'Hara, Robby Benson, Richard White, Jerry
Orbach, David Ogden Stiers, Angela Lansbury, Rex Everhart, Jesse Corti, and Jo Anne Worley.
Set in 18th-century France, an enchantress transforms a selfish
prince into a monster as punishment for his cruelty.
Years later, a young woman, Belle, offers the Beast her
own freedom in exchange for her father's.
To break the spell, the Beast must earn Belle's love before the last petal
falls from his enchanted rose, lest he remain a monster forever.
Walt Disney unsuccessfully attempted to adapt "Beauty and the Beast"
into an animated film during the 1930s and 1950s.
Inspired by the success of The Little Mermaid (1989), Disney enlisted Richard Purdum to adapt
the fairy tale, which he originally conceived as a non-musical period drama.
Dissatisfied with Purdum's efforts, Disney executive Jeffrey Katzenberg ordered that the entire film be reworked into a musical
with original songs by The Little Mermaid's songwriting team, lyricist Howard Ashman and composer Alan Menken.
First-time directors Trousdale and Wise replaced Purdum, and Woolverton's involvement made Beauty and the
Beast Disney's first animated film to utilize a completed screenplay prior to storyboarding.
The film was the second to use Computer Animation Production System (CAPS), which enabled seamless
blending of traditional and computer animation, particularly during its ballroom scene.
Beauty and the Beast is dedicated to Ashman, who died from
AIDS eight months before the film's release.
Beauty and the Beast premiered at the New York Film Festival with an unfinished
version on September 29, 1991, before its wide release on November 22.
It received widespread acclaim for its story, characters, music, and
animation, specifically for the ballroom sequence.
With an initial worldwide gross of $331 million, the film finished its run as the third highest-grossing
film of 1991 and the first animated film to gross over $100 million in the United States.
Subsequent re-releases (IMAX in 2002 and 3D in 2012) later
increased the film's all-time gross to $451 million.
Among its accolades, Beauty and the Beast was the first animated film to win the Golden Globe Award for Best Motion
Picture – Musical or Comedy and the first to receive a nomination for the Academy Award for Best Picture.
At the latter's 64th ceremony, the film received five other nominations, ultimately winning the
Academy Awards for Best Original Score and Best Original Song ("Beauty and the Beast").
In 1994, Beauty and the Beast became the first Disney film adapted into a Broadway
musical, which won a single Tony Award; the show ultimately ran for 13 years.
Other derivate works include three direct-to-video sequels, a television series, a
live-action remake in 2017, and a live-action/animated television special in 2022.
In 2002, Beauty and the Beast was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by
the Library of Congress for being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of princess, france, prince, castle, villain.
The tone is uplifting and emotional and intense.